Guide to the William C. Frederick Papers, 1971-1987 AIS.1999.22
ULS Archives & Special Collections
William C. Frederick Papers
1971-1987
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Frederick, William Crittenden
AIS.1999.22
1.25 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
William C. Frederick, Professor of Business Administration at the University of Pittsburgh, created these research files for a study of the Pittsburgh-area steel mill closings in the 1980s. Included are notes from ten interviews with business, labor and community leaders, and files on grassroots activist organizations.
Biography
William Crittenden Frederick, born 1925, received his PhD in economics from the University of Texas and taught at the University of Kansas City before becoming a professor of business administration at the University of Pittsburgh, 1963-mid-1990s. He also served for a time as the dean of the graduate school of business. Frederick's areas of scholarly interest included corporate social performance, business ethics, and managerial values. He is credited with helping found the business and society field of management studies in the United States. He authored, Values, Nature, and Culture in the American Corporation, and co-authored a widely used textbook, Business and Society. Frederick chaired the Social Issues in Management division of the Academy of Management and served as president of both the Society for Business Ethics and the Society for the Advancement of Socio-Economics.
Scope and Content Notes
William C. Frederick, University of Pittsburgh Professor of Business Administration, created these papers while doing research for his paper, "The New Social Responsibility and What Business Can and Should Do About It." The paper was presented before an audience primarily of Pittsburgh-area business executives on June 21, 1984. Series I. Interview Notes provides summaries of his interviews with ten business, labor, academic, religious, non-profit and grassroots leaders concerning the closing of Pittsburgh-area steel mills. Series II. Research contains a wide variety of material related to grassroots efforts to oppose the mill closings and increase aid to unemployed steelworkers in the Pittsburgh region.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William C. Frederick, April 6, 2000.
Previous Citation
William C. Frederick Papers, 1971-1987, AIS.1999.22, Archives Service Center, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh (Pa.); University of Pittsburgh; Business and Industry; Iron and steel workers -- United States; Labor; Steel industry and trade -- United States; Monongahela River Valley (W. Va. and Pa.); Personal papers; Frederick, William Crittenden; Mellon Bank; United Steel Workers Association; Network to Save the Mon/Ohio Valley; Roderick, David M.; Tri-State Conference on Steel; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Pittsburgh. Task Force on Unemployment and Economic Dislocation; United States Steel Corporation; University of Pittsburgh -- Faculty; Mon-Valley Unemployed Committee
- Interview Notes, 1984; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains brief, hand-written or typed notes summarizing in-person or telephone interviews with ten business, labor, academic, religious, non-profit and grassroots leaders focusing on the causes and impact of the steel mill closings in the Pittsburgh region. The interviews were not taped.
  - Ahlbrandt, Roger S., University of Pittsburgh, June 6, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Lois, Paul Lodico and Rich Pompanio, Mon Valley Unemployed Committee, June 7, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Christman, Ray, Allegheny Conference, June 11, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Deutsch, Barry I., Mellon Bank, June 18, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dorsey, Garrett, St. Stephen Roman Catholic Church, June 15, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Graham, Thomas C., United States Steel Corporation, June 8, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hoffman, United States Steel Corporation, June 13, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Olsen, John, Mellon Bank, June 12, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Smith, Jim, United Steel Workers of America, June 11, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Smith, John T., United Steel Workers of America, June 11, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Research, 1971-1987; II.
  This Series primarily documents the activities of grass-roots organizations which opposed steel mill closings and supported increased aid to unemployed steelworkers in the Pittsburgh region. The best documented organizations are the Mon Valley Unemployed Committee, Network to Save Mon/Ohio Valley, the Pittsburgh Presbytery's Task Force on Unemployment and Economic Dislocation, and the Tri-State Conference on Steel. Included are agendas, bibliographies, broadsheets, brochures, contact information, correspondence, flyers, news clippings, newsletters, notes, pamphlets, press releases, sermons, speeches and statistics. Of particular interest is the paper resulting from this research, The New Social Responsibility and What Business Can and Should Do About It, and a presentation by Chairman David M. Roderick of the United States Steel Corporation before the National Conference on the Dislocated Worker.
  - Biographies, 1971, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, May 31, 1984-Juny 10, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, July 11, 1984-May 8, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Denominational Ministry Strategy, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dislocated Workers Educational Training Program, Community College of Allegheny County, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Global Economy, Third Annual Conference on Industry and Society, Indiana University of Pennsylvania, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Homestead Project, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Interview Contact Information, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Leadership Pittsburgh, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Leaflets, Labor Organizations, c., 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Mon Valley Unemployed Committee, July 1983-October 1985 (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - National Conference on the Dislocated Worker, National Alliance of Business, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Network to Save the Mon/Ohio Valley, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - New Social Responsibility and What Business Can and Should Do About It, William C. Frederick, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Papers by others, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "Phil Murray: Our Leader" button, c., 1940s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Pittsburgh Presbytery's Task Force on Unemployment and Economic Dislocation, July 1984-December 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Prevention Alliance of Allegheny County, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Regional Reindustrialization Conference, Tri-State Conference on Steel, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Statistics, Unemployment, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tri-State Conference on Steel, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - United States Steel Corporation, A Time for Decision, c., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - United States Steel Corporation Annual Report, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - United Steelworkers of America Leadership Training Seminar on Service to Laid-Off Members, March 27, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Western Pennsylvania Advanced Technology Center, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)